hey everybody it's Ariannita la Gringa and welcome back to my YouTube channel
in today's video I will ask people around Cincinnati, Ohio what they do for a living and how much they make each year
let's go
hi, what's your name?
my name is Austin
hi Austin, what do you do for a living?
I work downtown at Divisions Maintenance Group and I manage a book of business for various different clients and I help them with their facility maintenance
when Americans ask "what do you do for a living?" they want to find out your job and what you do for work
what's your favorite part about your job?
probably my favorite part is just seeing my client's reaction when I solve a problem for them
and then what kind of projects do you work on?
well, right now I won't say the name